okay so we're going to meditate for
about five
minutes watch your
breath
e e
go to the golden
room just the brightness of the
gold will prevent subtle
dness e
look out the window at the sky deep sky
that
expansiveness prevents the over inward
turning of the mind which can bring on
agitation
look at the wide expanse of the Valley
and the mountains Beyond
you come back to the golden room and ask
your heart teacher to come
Gaz up into their eyes hold their eyes
with your
eyes there's no reason
to think or look at anything else just
stay there happily
contented
relax
happy
e e
if your mind
wanders use your sh to catch it use your
Gema to bring it
back and try to watch them doing
it so that you can get used to them and
and use them more
consciously
e e
come back to this
room and relx open your
eyes so he
if Nick were just you can't move okay I
mean you can't sit in a different place
uh if
were if Nick were just one
right and and again over the centuries
the
one is he one or many
normally he's just one right uh and over
the centuries they've come to say oh
Nick's just
one uh but what it meant more
specifically in the olden days was is
Nick his his the parts that make up Nick
or is Nick the sum total of them the one
thing which is the sum total of them
okay and uh we're going to work on the
sum total of them
Okay Go
Okay then if he
were uh one if NE were one he could
never appear to be separate things right
okay
so then he would have to be a one
without divisions which gets into a
question you see he's a paradox Nick is
a paradox
why we talked about it in Phoenix uh you
can't see Nick unless you you know how
they take they they tie people down to a
chair and they they track their eyes
track an object and their eyes you know
human eyes are going like this all the
time and what they're doing is uh to see
Nick you have to see a couple of
indicators of Nick okay you can't uh you
you need to you check the beard but
there's some other people with beards
and then you check the eyes and you knew
the eyes you know the eyes are not the
same so those and then he's wearing a
certain t-shirt and the other person's
not and so to to to to to determine he's
not another guy with a beard in the room
uh you have to your eyes have to go like
this and you have to pick up different
indicators of of Nick so we can say that
you can't see Nick without moving around
to different parts of Nick it's not
possible you can't just be seeing the
whole
nick uh because you wouldn't recognize
who he was you you have to check out
indicat taus and then based on that you
decide
Nick but you also can't so you can't see
the whole Nick if you don't look at the
indicators but when you look at
indicators you're not looking at a whole
Nick all right so there's a
contradiction going on
and and that's
what emptiness meditations or
emptiness lines of reasoning are meant
to point out the Paradox of how we do
things you know like it's not it's
actually not possible that you're seeing
Newton okay uh in a in the way you think
you are it's not possible if he were out
there uh and and if it were true that I
have to see his parts of him to identify
who he is
uh I can't see all the parts at once
when I look at his hands I can't look at
his eyes when I look at his eyes I can't
look at his ears and then uh I can't
look at them
altoe the fact that I think I'm seeing a
whole Nick is itself a
GTA the whole Nick that I think I see is
a GTA there can't be a whole Nick out it
looks like there's a whole Nick out
there but there can't be because if I
wasn't moving around to different parts
of him I couldn't identify him and if I
stuck with the hole I couldn't look at
his parts so I couldn't identify him so
if you look at the parts to identify him
you can't identify them if you look at
the hole you could never identify him
anyway so what you think you're doing is
impossible and that's all proes of these
are different ways of proving emptiness
you can't see Nick without looking at
his when you're looking at the parts you
can't see Nick
either because you're looking at the
parts of Nick okay so what you're doing
is impossible so what's really happening
let me let me describe what's really
happening and you'll feel more
comfortable
uh there's a stage in your career
there's a stage in your meditative
career and your spiritual career
there are five classical stages in your
spiritual career okay and they are
reflected in the
Mantra in
Chinese in Sanskrit okay
uh and the second one is important okay
at the end of the
second level of realization okay at the
end of the second level
you answer the Nick question okay how
you're perceiving Nick okay there's a
experience you have an experience so
I'll describe it okay I've described it
many times before I'll do it uh so
you're living with your
llama uh you're there cook
Etc uh which is proper okay and that's
how it goes and then
um so you've been studying really hard
especially chick
which is uh the subject I'm sorry
chich chich which is not the same uh but
it is the subject because how do you how
do you
see how would you say it qualities and
those things which are characteristic of
those qualities so for example GRE uh I
don't know yellow and things which
possess yellow okay how do you how do
you see those
things and you've been serving other
people a lot and you've been meditating
hard and you're up to the ninth level
plus nine plus okay so all of those
conditions are there and then
uh you go to make your llama a cup of
tea you're just standing there in front
of the stove making a cup of tea in Zen
they call it sator I
think uh but there's a debate about it
okay and I'll talk about that but anyway
you're standing in front of
the stove you're looking at a pot on the
stove and because of all that good stuff
you've been doing okay meditating
serving your teacher helping old people
studying hard meditating really hard
regular practice because of all those
factors suddenly you
realize that the PO in the
stove is a tiny little picture in the
back back of your mind okay I mean you
looking at the stove you're looking at
the pot and then you realize you're not
looking at a pot out there you're
watching a tiny image of a pot in your
mind and what's out
there is just some indicators of a pot
okay like you can't see a whole pot out
there you never can see a whole pot
anyway right the back of the pot might
be a a watermelon you don't know right
you only see the front half but your
mind synthesizes a nice full thing in
your mind's eye you see a whole pot so
anyway you're looking at this thing on
the stove you realize it only was ever
some round silver and some straight
black okay because the eyes cannot see
anything else than shapes and colors the
eyes cannot interpret an object you see
your your your cones and rods can only
detect
colors and shapes okay so you can't see
a pot there's no such thing you can't
see a pot because your your your eye
faculty the the the cones and rods in
the back of your eye cannot make
decisions they can just change according
to whether colors are presented to them
or or shapes are presented to them so
technically all you're really seeing is
round silver black straight okay and
then you you in that moment of deep
realization you catch your mind making
an image a per an impossibly perfect
image of a pot and laying it down on the
straight black and the Silver
Run okay it's overlaying it like what do
you call those things
uh when you project it on the wall
overhead
projector help me just like yeah
transparency okay so it's like your your
mind is placing a transparency of a over
the the straight stick and and the round
the red it's not a stick sorry straight
black and round silver okay and then and
that's all and and then within that
within the next within that day you see
EMP this directly those things happen at
the same on the same day
[Music]
okay so what all this aru or what all
this book is trying to describe is
that uh
Nick can't be the way you think he
is if if he was if you saw Nick by
looking at his Parts you couldn't see
the whole Nick if you can only see Nick
by looking at his parts then you can't
see the whole Nick but if you look at a
whole Nick you can't see his parts to
identify him what you're doing is not
possible he's not there uh it's you are
there's an image being uh a small bright
luminous image is
in the back of your mind and you are
overlaying it on some part okay and it's
impossibly perfect then then you start
the
fourth sorry you go to direct perception
of emptiness which is the third of the
five paths then you go into the gam
which means getting used to what you saw
and that can take seven lifetimes that
can typically could take 500
years and then uh
during that
time you struggle with the applications
of what you saw to real life you see
what I mean how can I apply okay so Nick
is just a luminous little picture in the
back of my
mind overlaid on some straight black and
round silver so what how am I supposed
to use that to help the world how am I
supposed to save the world with that see
and then guman which takes up to 490
years uh you are struggling with this
question and I guess the
First Progress you made is uh asking
yourself where did the Luminous picture
come from why am I having that luminous
picture see I mean why did I see a
silver pot why did my mind choose to
make a silver pot from the round silver
and the black straight okay and then you
start appreciating kic seeds mental
seeds you get more and more
sophisticated
about understanding mental
seeds and then in time that removes your
mental afflictions completely okay
why you realize the people are screaming
at you are coming from you then you
don't scream
back uh and then there's no more bad
stuff in your life and you reach nirvana
okay basically right uh no because you
don't respond anymore the way you used
to because you realize it's a picture
coming from you and that if you don't
like it you have to stop doing it okay
so that's all uh that's body so hard
then you're getting lighten and all that
uh so he's discussing the whole next few
pages are discussing is
Nick the whole
thing right or is he the individual part
if he's the whole thing I couldn't
perceive him
because I can only do that by looking at
his individual Parts if he's his
individual Parts I would never get to
the whole
thing got it okay
so if he was the whole
thing we used to say right yeah
that all the words I ever learned I
learned from ruche uh by being his
driver and his dishwasher people thought
I was
stupid uh spending you know 10 years
driving and washing dishes but he was
like my dictionary I never had a
dictionary you know and I would say
what's what's mean we were in a 7-Eleven
okay we were in a convenience store I
said R there's this there's this weird
phrase in the M
text what's that mean and he looks
around he says you got it right here you
know I said what do you mean zi means
one
substance and dop means different
manifestations and he says look all the
crap in this store you know you got
Twinkies you got cupcakes you got cherry
pies you got you know everything is the
same sugar flour and water in different
manifestations it's it's all the same
stuff exactly the same stuff with
slightly different flavoring you know
but it's all the same unhealthy stuff in
different packages and different shapes
and that's
it means same stuff means different
manifestations of the same
different you could say manifestations
of the same stuff so here it is in the
scripture
okay
um is he just one thing appearing in
different ways okay is he just one thing
appearing in different ways meaning uh
then we get to that part
about which
means is he appearing to be many when in
fact he is one
okay and if that were true then he can't
be
real if he were appearing as many when
in fact he were one then he couldn't be
real in the way in the way they because
real means what I left you with that
real means the way he appear ears in the
way he is uh match and when they don't
match that means he's unreal okay so if
he
were okay if he were one nick uh with
different parts of
Nick appearing as an arm okay if Nick
were one but different parts of Nick
were appearing as Nick's arm or Nick's
head or Nick's feet right then the the
appearance of a hole and the re sorry
the appearance of Multiplicity and the
reality of and the actuality of a of a
singularity would be a contradiction and
that's not real because that that
contradicts the the meaning of real the
definition I'll say it
again if there were just one
nick uh and then I had to check his
parts to find him then in a sense the
one Nick is appearing through each of
his parts right in in which case uh the
reality of Nick would be singular one
Nick but he would be expressing himself
as multiple
Parts in that case the way he appears to
me as multiple Nicks and the way he
really is one basic Nick substance would
be contradictory and then he would
become
unreal and then that's not real okay and
the other guy's trying to say Nick is
real all
right okay
if something existed in
reality then the way it appears and the
way it is should match
okay and if that were the case
if if Nick were what you say if Nick
were the hole okay if Nick were the hall
then it would be meaningless to talk
about Nick okay
why then when you said Nick's body and
mind it would be the equivalent of
saying it would be the equivalent of
saying the body and mind of the body and
mind
okay there's Nick's body and there's
Nick's mind okay I'm using body and mind
for the five scas because it's too
complicated but that's what it means
okay there's Nick Nick's body and
there's Nick's
mind do you say do we have the genitive
expression apostrophe s Nick's body and
Nick's mind right that would imply that
Nick is separate from them because he
possesses
them okay so there must be a separate
Nick who's the owner of the body and who
owns the mind because you use an
apostrophe
yes okay Nick's body and Nick's mind so
Nick must be someone other than the body
and
mind no and then you can say he's the
whole Nick as a whole possesses the
parts Nick's body mixed money right
um but if Nick were if if Nick were his
parts then when you said Nick's body and
Nick's mind you would be saying body's
body and mind's mind
okay is he related to his
part is Nick related to his part yes can
we think of Nick as a big thing that
possesses his
Parts yeah is that thing SE from the
parts or one with the
parts is the big Nick separate from the
parts of Mick Nick or is he the same as
the parts of Nick because if he's the
same as the parts of Nick he's multiple
then he's like
schizophrenic you know then there's all
kinds of Nicks running around okay all
right you're getting confused and you
think I'm just
blabbing
uh but it's what I'm trying to point out
is that what you think you he is is
wrong it's not the way you think of Nick
is not
possible you think
there's you think there's one big Nick
who who who possesses his body and
possesses his mind but at the same time
you can't say he's separate from his
body and his he is his body and his mind
so what you're essentially what you're
saying is when you say Nick's body
you're saying Nick's Nick and it's a
contradiction it's it's crazy you can't
say Nick's mind and Nick's body because
Nick is his body in his M
okay
okay all
right what you're doing is impossible
and that's proofs that you're doing
something
wrong so then he says to say Nick's body
and Nick's Nick would be the same
thing all
right then it would
become uh meaningless to draw a
distinction between uh Nick and Nick's
body if Nick's body were Nick it'd be
meaningless to talk about Nick and
Nick's
body uh if Nick's body wasn't Nick then
where else is
name
okay
okay then they quot AR n so N is a real
Arya you
know and I think the proof of it is that
the book he wrote was 20 you know seven
pages long and
uh and it's just these weird statements
you know
it's just weird impossible statements
that sound bizarre to us because we're
bizarre okay so here's one of
them which is a good time to go back can
you fire up that confuser just fired up
in the hand of you don't have to plug it
in I left a couple paragraphs at the end
of Phoenix okay which we skipped and I I
just want to get them to you I want to
make sure you have them all right
basically they just talk talk about
how lucky we are that there were at
least two or three Aras in history so
that we have
somebody to ask about what is emptiness
right because if it weren't for having a
few people around who had seen emptiness
directly you could imagine how weird
these books would
be okay I mean if someone didn't really
know what it meant what happens in
historically is there comes an Arya they
make statements and then people who are
not repeat them to other people and they
get mixed up and then another Arya comes
along in about 700 years and straightens
it out and
then you see and then the whole thing
happens again okay so
uh he's about to quote N who is an A and
I wanted to uh what we did in Phoenix we
got to a a part in the text in the
beginning of the emptiness section where
he just said Thank thank goodness we've
had a few AAS in history uh to
straighten things out for us okay like
he he and I I left a few sentences out
of there and I just wanted to give it
to so just for a historical record so
you can get it into the right
place uh this is page 365a which is
slightly before what we started with
here then
therefore uh the
unmatched uh explanation of the true
thought which clarifies that s that most
profound object meaning emptiness okay
and the author Pabon is making a pun and
a joke
because he said the best book which
clarifies the true thought of that Deep
thing that's the name of Jetson capa's
most famous book on emptiness
he's he he he wo the name into a phrase
as a joke okay and then he
says the The Works of
tonapa are the ultimate means of
clarifying the meaning of emptiness okay
but that's actually the name one of his
best books
there are three sorry yeah there are
3,000 different books in the Canon from
ancient India commentaries there are
1,500 sutras and tantas spoken by Lord
Buddha we still have 1,500 suas and
tantas spoken by Lord Buddha in tibetan
translation and they don't exist in the
s good anymore maybe
10% due to the mul invasion of India
[Music]
okay then we have about 3,000
commentaries upon them from ancient
India okay over the period of 15
centuries so we have those books we have
those two Kier and Tangier these are the
two great cannons Jetson Kapa studied
the entire Tanger he went through the
whole body of 3,000
commentaries from India trying to find a
good explanation of emptiness right okay
J and then what he found out
was he couldn't find almost any that he
felt were
SEMA which means what P which means cra
then he asked his yidam okay yidam means
uh like a guardian angel okay
to
so he went to the
boss you he now he was confused he went
to thousands of books and he said I
can't really get a good explanation
emptiness so he did what everybody
should learn to do he asked his Guardian
Angel you know he got he he had he he
worked to find a Guardian Angel the
first book ever written by tonapa is a
praise of uh sis fatti a goddess of
music and poetry and he made contact
with her and then he would ask her
things you know so
so the whole thing is a lot easier if
you just find a guardian angel okay and
uh you then you just ask them questions
you know and they and then the whole
thing is easier so he went to his
Guardian Angel who was jambang M right
kand then he he said you know I have a
problem I'm I'm trying to understand
emptiness and I I can't find I don't
feel that all any of these books is
really accurate you're talking the
danger
okay
jel J Lama Maj said
to there's this dude named dhak sorry
Chandra okay there's somebody named
Chandra all right he lives in a in a
Buddha
Paradise he is a very high level bhis
SAA and uh he under he's a capable of
undertaking he he acts out the Deeds of
all the bodh saas he is of great
courage which is also by the way upon
pun because that was a name of the
Buddha in olden
times uh when the Buddha gave his life
to the tigress and her cups he was
called n so it's a it's a big he's not
just saying he was courageous he's
making it an
illusion this body will appear on this
Earth to explain the words of nagaj he
will clarify what nagaj meant
like 500 years after
okay and he has come to your world just
to do that he he came to your world just
to clarify
that then that those commentaries you
can trust okay you you can trust Master
Chand that's that's his yam his guardian
angel giving him advice you know you can
trust find the books of CH you can trust
them
okay and therefore Ever
After took the books of Master chandi
and his heart teacher right MRI his
Guardian Angel he took them as beinga P
truth okay truth J
when when people like us guys he uses
the wrong typ okay when people are like
us uh when we are struggling to learn
about
emptiness uh we we open the works of
zapa and his lineage right and
go uh when we try to learn them they are
difficult they're difficult to crack
okay it's difficult to figure out what
they
mean these books
are means
uh linga
[Music]
means what do you call unfathomable
how's that
unfathomable link can also mean depth of
the ocean
so uh it's very very rare
word uh so they are linga and profound
therefore they are not easily
understood but okay you know what he's
gonna say
but
sh but if you spend time with them and
you keep trying to chip away at them
okay you will discover jewels of
understanding that you won't find
anywhere else okay so
take you know you call it confront these
explanations and don't run away from
them they're hard and and crack them and
keep chipping away we have this thing in
in America or I don't know in Eng I
don't know when when I grew up I never
read a book twice you know I mean
I when you're a child or a young person
in America when I was growing up you
read a
book and you if you understood it you
got A's in school and if you didn't
understand it so much you got
Seas but they didn't ask you to keep
reading it over and over you know what I
mean and uh so my relationship was with
books was like my relationship with
movies I never see a movie twice except
Gandhi or you know Date with an Angel
that's a different thing uh it's a great
anyway that's a y movie that's a
guardian angel movie but uh you know
normally I I groc a whole movie after I
see it once I don't feel like I have to
see it again because it's not worth it
it's not worth the time and but but a
but a a Tona book is a different thing
you can't relate to it in a single City
there's no such things you can spend the
rest of your life rereading it and you
will keep finding new things that you
didn't understand before it's like layer
upon layer upon layer okay people ask me
you
know people ask me you want to go to the
bookstore gu you Michel I say no and
they say I thought you like book I said
yes but I have
SOA you know and then they say oh you're
just being secretari or something or you
know you're just
being you know and I'm like no you don't
understand you know you can you can read
Sona for the rest of your life you can
read one book of Sona for the rest of
your life and it suffices everything you
want is
there you know so anyway I just drink
hot chocolate he knows we go I drink hot
chocolate he goes looks at books but
he's got this m manga
thing yeah okay manga I might look at
okay
the uh Su is a very rare word and it
means uh it's not the Su and gel it has
a different spelling
uh sub means like almost mystical
Firepower there's no English word
mystical
Firepower uh so capa's books have
Firepower uh which can which can bring
you understandings of emptiness that you
can't get anywhere else okay so that
completes a section which I didn't
finish in Phoenix from from before okay
from up above why did I say that because
he's about to quote the Gina okay are in
a Garder